Finding Aid for Upjohn Family Papers 1795-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Upjohn Family Papers 1795-1974
Upjohn family. [Robert U. Redpath, collector]
1 oversize volumes
7.1 linear feet
Papers of the Upjohn family of Hastings and Kalamazoo, Michigan, collected by Dr. E. Gifford Upjohn. Papers and genealogical materials of Upjohn and related families, especially the Mills family, Kirby family, and Clough family; include materials concerning family activities, medical practice, and daily life; also papers concerning the work of Clough family members as missionaries to southern India; and selected Upjohn Pharmaceutical Company historical records; and photographs.
85579 Aa 2 AC
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Dr. E. Gifford Upjohn (donor 921 ) in 1977.
The collection is open for research.
The Upjohn family papers, collected and preserved by Dr. E. Gifford Upjohn, consist of materials brought together by various family members primarily for genealogical purposes. More than a "family archive" because of the importance of the Upjohns as founders of the Upjohn Pharmaceutical Company in Kalamazoo, the collection includes material spanning the period from the early 1800s to the present. The Upjohn Collection consists of three feet of manuscripts, two feet of family related books and bound manuscripts, and two feet of photographs.
Because of its diversity, the collection has been divided into five series of papers: Upjohn family; Families related to the Upjohns; Upjohn Company; Printed Materials; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Baptists--Missions--India.; Clough, J. E. (John Everett), 1836-1910.; Clough family.; Hastings (Mich.); India.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Kirby family.; Medicine--Michigan.; Mills family.; Missionaries--India.; Pharmacy.; Physicians--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Upjohn, E. Gifford.; Upjohn, Gratia Clough, 1874-1957.; Upjohn, Henry Uriah, 1843-1887.; Upjohn, Lawrence Northcote, 1873-1967.; Upjohn, Millie Kirby, 1852-1920.; Upjohn, Uriah, 1808-1896.; Upjohn, William, 1770-1847.; Upjohn, William, 1807-1887.; Upjohn Company.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Baptists--Missions--India.; Clough, J. E. (John Everett), 1836-1910.; Clough family.; India.; Kalamazoo High School (Kalamazoo, Mich.). Class of 1892.; Kirby family.; Missionaries--India.; Missions--India.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medicine and Surgery. Class of 1900.; Upjohn, Gratia Clough, 1874-1957.; Upjohn, Henry Uriah, 1843-1887.; Upjohn, Lawrence Northcote, 1873-1967.; Upjohn, Millie Kirby, 1852-1920.; Upjohn, Uriah, 1808-1896.; Upjohn, William, 1807-1887.; Upjohn Company.
Genre/Form:
Ambrotypes.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Upjohn family
  The first series, Upjohn family, has been arranged by generation, beginning with the Rev. William Upjohn, continuing with his sons, William and Uriah, then with the children of Uriah (principally Henry U. Upjohn), and with the children of Henry (principally Lawrence N. Upjohn). The Rev. William Upjohn (1770-1847) was a civil engineer and preacher in Shaftsbury, England. His papers (folders 1-6 to 1-11) include journals for the period, 1821-1847, sermon outlines, and a personal daybook (1823-1832).
  William Upjohn had two sons. One of these, Uriah Upjohn (18081896) was a physician who practiced in Richland, Michigan. His papers (folders 1-17 to 1-19) include a daybook, 1834-1839, correspondence, and legal materials from an 1881 court case.
  Among the children of Uriah was Henry U. Upjohn (1843-1887) also a Richland physician. His papers (folders 1-22 to 1-29) contain correspondence, 1865-1885, and a daybook, 1871-1887. Lawrence N. Upjohn (1873-1967) was son of Henry U. Upjohn and president of the Upjohn Company. His papers (folders 2-1 to 2-12) include correspondence, the transcript of an oral interview, and personal account books.
  In addition, this series includes materials for other Upjohn family members. As noted, these have been arranged by generation. Materials relating to spouses have been placed after the appropriate Upjohn husband or wife, unless otherwise indicated.
  - Historical materials
    - American branch (Box 1)
      (1-1; 1-2; 1-3)
    - European branch (Box 1)
      (1-4; 1-5)
  - William Upjohn (1770-1847)
    - Biographical materials (Box 1)
      (1-6)
    - Papers 1795-1796, 1809 (Box 1)
      (1-7)
    - Journal July 24, 1820-October 6, 1821 (Box 1)
      (1-8)
    - Journal October 28, 1821-January 28, 1847 (Box 1)
      (1-9)
    - Sermon Outlines circa 1802 (Box 1)
      (1-10)
    - Daybook 1823-1832 (Box 1)
      (1-11)
  - William Upjohn (1807-1887), son of William Upjohn
    - Biographical materials (Box 1)
      (1-12)
    - Papers circa 1860s (Box 1)
      (1-13)
    - Journal entry "Voyage to America 1830" (Box 1)
      (1-14)
    - Journal entry 1830 (Box 1)
      (1-15)
    - Journal entry 1840 (Box 1)
      (1-16)
  - Dr. Uriah Upjohn (1808-1896), son of William Upjohn (1770-1847)
    - Biography (Box 1)
      (1-17)
    - Papers (Box 1)
      (1-18)
    - Court Case 1881 (Box 1)
      (1-19)
    - Day Book 1834-1839 (Box 4)
  - Maria Mills, wife of Uriah Upjohn
    - Papers relating to Mills family (Box 2)
      (folders 19-20)
  - Helen Maria Upjohn (1839-1901), daughter of Uriah Upjohn
    - Scrapbook (Box 4)
  - Mary Northcote Upjohn (1840-1939), daughter of Uriah Upjohn
    - Materials on descendants (Box 1)
      (1-20)
  - Alice Upjohn (1841-1920), daughter of Uriah Upjohn
    - Papers (Box 1)
      (1-21)
  - Henry Uriah Upjohn (1843-1887) son of Uriah Upjohn
    - Biographical materials (Box 1)
      (1-22)
    - Correspondence 1865-1869 (Box 1)
      (1-23)
    - Correspondence 1870-1879 (Box 1)
      (1-24)
    - Correspondence 1880-1885 (Box 1)
      (1-25)
    - Papers 1868-1884 (Box 1)
      (1-26)
    - Patent Office communications 1867-1878 (Box 1)
      (1-27)
    - Patent Office communications 1867-1878 (Box 1)
      (1-28)
    - School Book 1867 (Box 4)
    - Bank-Book 1883-1884 (Box 1)
      (1-29)
    - Daybook "A" 1871-1873 (Box 4)
    - Daybook "C" 1873-1877 (Box 4)
    - Daybook "D" 1877-1887 (Box 4)
  - Pamelia "Millie" Kirby (1852-1920) wife of Henry U. Upjohn
    (For related Kirby family materials see 2-21 to 2-31)
    - Biographical materials (Box 1)
      (1-30)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
      (1-31)
    - Diary 1872-1887 (Box 1)
      (1-32)
    - Estate (Box 1)
      (1-33)
    - Property Deeds (Box 1)
      (1-34)
    - Notebook 1873-1875 (Box 4)
    - Accounts with Renters 1882-1898 (Box 4)
  - Amelia Upjohn (1848-1876), daughter of Uriah Upjohn
    - Papers (Box 1)
      (1-35)
    - Account book (Box 4)
    - Materials on descendants (Box 1)
      (1-36)
  - Sarah Upjohn (1850-1908), daughter of Uriah Upjohn
    - Materials on descendants (Box 1)
      (1-37)
    - Correspondence 1956-1959 (Box 1)
      (1-38)
    - Correspondence 1960-1965 (Box 1)
      (1-39)
    - Correspondence 1966-1974 (Box 1)
      (1-40)
  - William E. Upjohn (1853-1932), son of Uriah Upjohn
    - Biographical materials (Box 1)
      (1-41)
    - Papers (Box 1)
      (1-42)
    - Children of W. E. Upjohn
      - Rachel Winifred Upjohn (1880-1929), daughter of W.E. Upjohn (Box 1)
        (1-43)
      - Harold Upjohn (1884-1928), son of W.E. Upjohn (Box 1)
        (1-44)
      - Dorothy Upjohn (1890), daughter of W.E. Upjohn (Box 1)
        (1-45)
      - Genevieve Upjohn (1894), daughter of W.E. Upjohn (Box 1)
        (1-46)
  - Frederick Lawrence Upjohn (1857-1917), son of Uriah Upjohn
    - Papers (Box 1)
      (1-47)
  - James Townley Upjohn (1857-1936) son of Uriah Upjohn
    - Biographical materials (Box 1)
      (1-48)
    - Materials on descendants
      - Genealogical materials (Box 1)
        (1-49)
      - Papers (Box 1)
        (1-50)
  - Lawrence Northcote Upjohn (1873-1967), son of Henry U. Upjohn
    - Biographical materials; also tape funeral eulogy tape 1967 (Box 2)
      (2-1)
    - Correspondence
      - 1896-1900 (Box 2)
        (2-2)
      - 1905-1910 (Box 2)
        (2-3)
      - 1911-1916 (Box 2)
        (2-4)
      - 1917-1918 (Box 2)
        (2-5)
      - 1941-1960 (Box 2)
        (2-6)
    - Printed materials (Box 2)
      (2-7)
    - Interview by Dr. Dunbar August 3, 1963 (Box 2)
      (2-8)
    - Kalamazoo High School Centennial Program 1959 (Box 2)
      (2-9)
    - Account Book 1911 (Box 2)
      (2-10)
    - Account Book 1919 (Box 2)
      (2-11)
    - Account Book 1937 (Box 2)
      (2-12)
  - Gratis Clough (1874-1957), wife of Lawrence N. Upjohn
    (other Clough family papers located in Related Family Branches series)
    - Biographical materials (Box 2)
      (2-13)
    - Correspondence
      - 1898-1900 (Box 2)
        (2-14)
      - 1902-1910 (Box 2)
        (2-15)
      - 1911-1917 (Box 2)
        (2-16)
      - 1932-1957 (Box 2)
        (2-17)
    - Miscellaneous materials (Box 2)
      (2-18)
  - E. Gifford Upjohn
    - Papers (Box 2)
      (2-18a)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Daybook circa 1837 (Volume 1)
      (also used as scrapbook)
    - University of Michigan Lecture notes (family member unknown) (Box 4)
      (located with bound records)
    - Citations, etc. (Box 8)
- Related family branches
  The second series, Related Family Members, consist of files concerning families who married into the Upjohn family. These include the Mills family (Maria Mills married Uriah Upjohn in 1837), the Kirby family (Pamelia "Millie" Kirby married Henry U. Upjohn in 1872), the Gilmore family, and the Clough family (Gratia Clough married Lawrence N. Upjohn in 1900). The Clough family files were of sufficient size to be themselves divided into three groups of papers: (a) Clough family, (b) John E. Clough, and (c) related branches of the Clough family.
  The Clough family papers are largely of a genealogical nature, and include correspondence, 1900-1973, publications of The Bulletin of the John Clough Genealogical Society, 1946-1955, and printed materials. John E. Clough (1836-1910) was father of Gratia Clough Upjohn. His papers relate to the missionary movement in Southern India during the latter half of the nineteenth century to the 1930s, and consist of correspondence, 1898-1905, biographical materials, printed literature of the American Baptist Foreign Mission, and its branches in Telugu and Ongole. Included are books written by John E. Clough on the missionary movement. The third group of materials concerns four families related to the Cloughs. The family names are Sunderland, Sturgeon, Atwood and Martin. These files include printed materials and correspondence pertaining to family history.
  - Mills family materials (Box 2)
    (2-19; 2-20)
  - Kirby family
    - Family history manuscript (Box 2)
      (2-21)
    - Family history (Box 2)
      (2-22)
    - Family historical materials (Box 2)
      (2-23)
    - Correspondence 1866-1960 (Box 2)
      (2-24)
    - Biographies (Box 2)
      (2-25)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
      (2-26)
    - Documents (Box 2)
      (2-27)
    - Mary S. Kirby, family historian
      - Biographical materials (Box 2)
        (2-28)
      - Correspondence 1937-1949 (Box 2)
        (2-29)
      - Scrapbook (Box 2)
        (2-30)
    - Sweetland family branch (Box 2)
      (2-31)
  - Gilmore family materials (Box 2)
    (2-32)
  - Clough family
    - Family history materials (Box 2)
      (2-33; 2-34; 2-35)
    - Genealogical notes in Bibles, photocopies (Box 2)
      (2-36)
    - Correspondence
      - 1900-1930 (Box 2)
        (2-37)
      - 1931-1939 (Box 2)
        (2-38)
      - 1940-1941 (Box 2)
        (2-39)
      - 1942-1944 (Box 3)
        (3-1)
      - 1951-1955 (Box 3)
        (3-2)
      - 1965-1973 (Box 3)
        (3-3)
    - The Bulletin of the John Clough Genealogical Society 1946-1955 (Box 3)
      (3-4)
    - Printed materials relating to Clough family history (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
      (3-5)
    - Miscellaneous history materials (Box 3)
      (3-6)
  - John E. Clough (1836-1910) father of Gratis Clough
    - Biographical materials (Box 3)
      (3-7)
    - Correspondence 1876, 1898-1905 (Box 3)
      (3-8)
    - Writings (Box 3)
      (3-9)
    - "Lone Star" Publication (Box 3)
      (3-10)
    - Miscellaneous materials (Box 3)
      (3-11)
    - Printed material relating to J.E. Clough (Box 5)
    - Clough Memorial Hospital
      - Correspondence 1938-1953 (Box 3)
        (3-12)
      - Printed materials (Box 3)
        (3-13)
    - Clough Training School (Box 3)
      (3-14)
    - "Missions" publication (Box 3)
      (3-15)
    - "The Examiner" publication (Box 3)
      (3-16)
    - "The Watchman Examiner" publication (Box 3)
      (13-17)
    - Printed material
      (3-18)
      - American Baptist Foreign Mission 1934 (Box 3)
      - The Baptist Missionary Review April 1917, May 1928 (Box 3)
      - Report of the American Baptist Telugu Mission 1900, 1905, 1917, 1919-1921, 1929-1931, 1933-1936 (Box 3)
      - Ongole Mission Field Annual Report 1913, 1915-1916, 1921, 1924-1929, 1931 (Box 3)
      - Ongole: The Story of a Great Mission Station 1923, 1930 (Box 3)
      - Handbook on the Station work at Ongole, India 1902 (Box 3)
      - Telugu Hymns 1898 (Box 3)
      - History of Madira Mission 1936 (Box 3)
      - Great Foreign Missionaries in India 1928 (Box 3)
      - Ongole on the Air 1866-1932, 1932 (Box 3)
      - Field Survey/South India 1930 (Box 3)
  - Sunderland Family (Box 3)
    (3-19)
    (see also printed material in box 5)
  - Sturgeon family (Box 3)
    (3-20)
  - Atwood family (Box 3)
    (3-21)
  - Martin family (Box 3)
    (3-22)
- Upjohn Company
  The third series in the Upjohn collection relates to the Upjohn Company. Materials in this group are limited and include a history of the company published in 1970, miscellaneous documents of the 18801s, and newspaper clippings.
  - Company History 1970 (Box 3)
    (3-23)
  - "The Upjohn Pill and Granule Co."
    - Paper 1880s (Box 3)
      (3-24)
    - Sales Pamphlets 1886 (Box 3)
      (3-25)
  - Upjohn News: 75th Anniversary Publication (Box 3)
    (3-26)
  - History of Brook Lodge (Box 3)
    (3-27)
  - Directors and Officers of the Upjohn Co. (Box 3)
    (3-28)
  - Internal Annual Report 1953 (Box 3)
    (3-29)
  - Articles (Box 3)
    (3-30)
- Printed material:
  - Clough family
    - The Genealogy of the Descendants of John Clough of Salisbury, Massachusetts. Littleton, N.H. 1952, 1966, 2 volumes (Box 5)
    - Eva Clough Speare, ed. The Story of the Family of John Clough of Salisbury, Massachusetts. Littleton, N.H., 1943 (Box 5)
    - The Poetical Works of Arthur Hugh Clough, with a memoir by Francis Turner Palgrave. London, Undated (Box 5)
  - John E. Clough
    - John E. Clough. Social Christianity in the Orient. New York, 1914 (Box 5)
    - Herbert W. Hines. Clough, Kingdom-Builder in South India, Philadelphia, 1929 (Box 5)
    - Emma Rauschenbusch-Clough. While Sewing Sandals, or Tales of a Telugu Pariah Tribe. London, 1899 (Box 5)
    - James M. Baker. Contending the Grade in India. 1947. (Box 5)
  - Sunderland family
    - James Sunderland. Annals of a Life of Faith, An Autobiography Kansas City, Mo., 1923 (Box 5)
    - James Sunderland, et al. Biographical sketches and Recollections of the Lives of Thomas Sunderland (2d) and Sarah Broadhead (Lovell) Kansas City, Mo., 1914 (Box 5)
  - Sturgeon family
    - Walter J. Sturgeon. A Genealogical History of the Sturgeons of North America. Cincinnati, 1926 (Box 5)
- Photographs
  Portraits of family members and members of related families, especially Clough and Kirby families; also photos of the family of John Everett Clough, Baptist missionary in Ongole, India, 1890s-1900s.
  - Individuals
    - Barrett, Alice Upjohn, family (Box 6)
    - Clough, Allen Everett (Box 6)
    - Clough, John Everett (1836-1910) (Box 6)
    - Clough, John Everett (1836-1910), family (Box 6)
    - Clough family miscellaneous (Box 6)
      (see also oversize photos in box 8)
    - Gilmore family (Box 6)
    - Kirby, John (1787-1869), family (Box 6)
    - Kirby, John (1787-1869), home, ambrotype (Box 6)
    - Kirby, Mary S. (1862-1956) (Box 6)
    - Kirby, William Gifford (1822-1907), family (Box 6)
    - Kirby, William Gifford (1822-1907), home (Box 6)
    - Kirby, William S. (b. 1857), family (Box 6)
    - Kirby family miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Kirkland, Helen Upjohn (Box 6)
    - Mills family (Box 6)
    - Redpath family (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Frederick L, family (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Genevieve Gilmore (1894-) (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Genevieve Gilmore (1894-) with daughter Martha Gilmore Parfet (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Gratia Clough, as a child (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Gratia Clough, as an adult, includes tintypes (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Henry (1843-1887) (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Henry (1843-1887), family (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Henry (1843-1887), home (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Lawrence N (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Lawrence N., family (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Mary Standard (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Meriah Mills (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Pamelia (Millie) Kirby (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Uriah (1808-1896) (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Uriah (1808-1896), engraving plate (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Uriah (1808-1896), family (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, Uriah (1808-1896), home (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, William (1770-1847), home in Shaftsbury, England (Box 6)
      (see also glass negatives ng51-ng59)
    - Upjohn, William (1807-1882) (Box 6)
    - Upjohn, William E. (1853-1932) (Box 6)
  - Topical file
    - India
      - Clough family (Box 6)
      - Mission and school at Ongole (Box 6)
      - People (Box 6)
      - Scenery and miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Kalamazoo High School Class of 1892 (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan Medical Class of 1900 (Box 6)
    - Upjohn Co. (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous homes (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous identified portraits (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous unidentified portraits (Box 6)
  - Albums
    - Barrett, Wright, album (Box 7)
    - Clough family album (Box 7)
    - Clough family India album, 2 volumes (Box 7)
    - Kirkland, Helen Upjohn, album (Box 7)
    - Upjohn, Henry U., family album (Box 7)
    - Upjohn, Pamelia Kirby, family album (Box 7)
The Bentley Library has additional Upjohn family papers collected by family members Robert U. Redplath and Robert U. Light